University of Connecticut, Associate Vice President for Academic Affairs Records [David Carter Papers] 1998.0259
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Libraries
University of Connecticut, Associate Vice President for Academic Affairs Records [David Carter]
undated, 1966-1983
1998.0259
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Libraries
0.75 Linear feet
The Associate Vice President for Academic Affairs assists the Vice President for Academic Affairs at the University of Connecticut. The Vice President for Academic Affairs, formerly and currently the Provost, was the chief academic officer of the University and reported directly to the University President. The collection contains minutes, notes, correspondence, reports and questionnaires associated with activities that were the responsibilities of the position held by Dr. Carter.
History
The Associate Vice President for Academic Affairs assists the Vice President for Academic Affairs at the University of Connecticut. The Vice President for Academic Affairs, formerly and currently the Provost, was the chief academic officer of the University and reported directly to the University President. The Office of the Provost was established in 1950 when the Provost assumed the functions of the Dean of the University. In 1975, the Office of the Provost was abolished and its functions were assigned to the new Vice President for Academic Affairs and the Vice President of Finance and Administration.
The office is responsible for university matters pertaining to academic activities and policy, including jurisdiction over the various schools, as well as faculty and student matters. In addition, the office is responsible for the daily internal operations of the University Senate and the Board of Trustees. In the 1990s, these responsibilities were reorganized and the office designated as the Chancellor and Provost for University Affairs. While the title of Chancellor has since been dropped, the Provost is also the Executive Vice President for Academic Affairs. Additional information on the responsibilities of the Office is available at: http://www.provost.uconn.edu/.
Born in Dayton, Ohio, David Carter was raised by his mother and his three older brothers. He earned a bachelor’s degree in elementary education from Central State University in Ohio, an M.Ed. degree in curriculum and supervision from Miami (Ohio) University, and a Ph.D. in educational development and educational administration from Ohio State University. David Carter’s career as a professional educator spans 45 years, beginning in Ohio and, since 1977, in Connecticut. He became the fifth president of Eastern Connecticut State University on April 2, 1988, and was the first African-American president of a four-year institution of higher education in Connecticut. He served as president for nearly 18 years, leading Eastern from a small university into a thriving academic institution with newly constructed first-rate facilities attracting a dynamic residential population from across the state, now designated as Connecticut’s public liberal arts university. He spent 11 years at the University of Connecticut before becoming the President of ECSU, and served as a professor of educational administration and associate dean in the School of Education, in addition to serving as associate vice president for academic affairs. Before joining the faculty at the University of Connecticut, he was an associate professor in the college of education at Pennsylvania State University.
Scope and Content Note
The collection contains minutes, notes, correspondence, reports and questionnaires associated with activities that were the responsibilities of the position held by Dr. Carter.
Access
The collection is open and available for research.
Provenance and Acquisition
The records were transferred by the Provost's office at some time prior to 1998.
Related Material
Archives & Special Collections has a substantial collection of materials pertaining to the University, its history, administration, faculty, staff and students. For detailed information on these collections please contact the curator or ask at the Reading Room desk.
University of Connecticut.; Administrative records.; Archives (institutions).; University of Connecticut.
- Series I: Inventory, undated, 1966-1983
  - Library, 1966-1975 (Box 1)
  - New Programs, 1968-1978 (Box 1)
  - Questionnaires, 1978 (Box 1)
  - Institutional Policy Committee, 1983 (Box 2)
  - Amino-Acid Analyzer Service, 1977-1978
  - Proposal for changing degree auditing, 1976 (Box 2)
  - Women's Studies Program, 1979-1981 (Box 2)
  - Over 62 Educational program, 1978-1979 (Box 2)
  - Afro American Cultural Center Policy Advisory Board, undated, 1982 (Box 2)